Finding Aid for Keeve Milton Siegel papers, 1953-1983
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Keeve Milton Siegel papers 1953-1983
Siegel, K.M. (Keeve Milton), 1923-
1.5 linear feet
89273 Aa 2
Keeve Milton Siegel was an inventor, physicist and professor of electrical engineering. Siegel’s papers consist of correspondence, memorandums, newspaper clippings, scientific reports, and files covering his academic, corporate and personal dealings.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated in 1976 by Ruth B. Siegel (donor no. 5810 ); additional materials were received in June, 2008.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Keeve Milton Siegel, known as Kip among his friends, was born in New York City on January 9, 1924. In 1948, Siegel graduated from Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute with a Bachelor of Science in theoretical physics. He went on to receive his master's degree in physics from the school in 1950. After graduating, Siegel married Ruth E. Boerker on June 22, 1951. The couple had two sons Leigh and David.
Also in 1951, Siegel moved to Ann Arbor to begin his first position with the University of Michigan as a research associate at UM Engineering Research Institute. As a research associate, Siegel headed the upper atmosphere research group and UM Radiation Laboratory from 1951-1956. In 1957, Siegel was appointed professor of electric engineering, a post he held until 1967. While a professor at the University, Siegel founded Conductron Corporation in 1960. Under his direction as President of Conductron, the corporation became one the area's largest industries. However, in 1967, the McDonnell-Douglas Corporation purchased Conductron and moved it out of Ann Arbor.
After leaving Conductron Corporation, Siegel founded KMS Industries in 1969. He became known internationally for his inventions in the field of optics. As chairman of KMS, Siegel focused much of his research on the development of laser induced nuclear fusion. Siegel believed passionately in the need to develop nuclear fusion as a clean and renewable source of energy. The research done at KMS on nuclear fusion was the only privately funded venture of its kind in the United States.
Siegel died March 14, 1975.
The Keeve Milton Siegel Papers document Siegel's corporate, academic, and personal activities between the years 1953 to his death in 1975. The collection consists primarily of correspondence, memorandums, newspaper clippings, and scientific reports. The collection contains the following series: Corporate Activities, Research, and Personal/Biographical.
Subjects:
Astronomy--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Moon.; Physicists.; Conductron Corporation.; KMS Industries.; Laser fusion.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Contributors:
Urey, Harold Clayton, 1893-1981.
Genre Terms:
Sound recordings.
- Corporate Activities, 1958-1980
  Corporate Activities series documents Siegel's commercial dealings and multiple business ventures. The series contains two subseries: KMS and Other corporations. Sub-series KMS covers Siegel's activities as founder and chairman of KMS Industries and consists of materials related to the company's major research projects like laser induced nuclear fusion and thermonuclear energy. Sub-series Other corporation reflects Siegel's diverse corporate profile and consists of various background material on the different corporations Siegel invested in and correspondence related to Siegel's role as president of Conduction Corporation.
  - KMS, 1958-1980
    - Atomic Energy Act, 1970-1974 (Box 1)
    - Delft URSI Meeting, 1958-1966 (Box 1)
    - General, 1969-1981, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - KMSiegel Horses, 1966-1973 (Box 1)
    - Laser Fusion, 1974-1975, 4 folders (Box 1)
    - Middle East Business, 1974-1980, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Nuclear Fusion Systems, 1973-1974 (Box 1)
    - Siegel's Notes (fragments), ca. 1970s (Box 1)
    - Texas Gas, 1974-1983 (Box 1)
    - Thermonuclear Energy and Hydrogen Research, 1973-1974 (Box 1)
    - War Protest, 1972, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Other corporations, 1962-1975
    - Conductron Corporation, 1962-1967 (Box 1)
    - Datamax Corporation, 1971-1975, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Leisuretron, 1968-1973 (Box 1)
    - Mechanical Technology Incorporated, 1968-1969 (Box 1)
    - Technion Israel Institute of Technology, 1970-1975 (Box 1)
- Research
  Research series contains files from Siegel's office at the University of Michigan and correspondence related to his work for the Center for Research on Conflict Resolution. The Report Files consist of scientific research reports written by Siegel and by other members of the academic community and are arranged alphabetically by the last name of the researcher.
  - Center for Research on Conflict Resolution, 1964-1967 (Box 1)
  - Lunar Research, 1960-1969 (Box 1)
  - Report Files, 1953-1965
    - A (Box 1)
    - B (Box 1)
    - C, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - G (Box 2)
    - K, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - L, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - M-P (Box 2)
    - R (Box 2)
    - S, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - U-W (Box 2)
- Personal/Background, 1961-1978
  Personal/Biographical series reflects Siegel's desire to serve the University, his local religious community and Israel. The series contains newspaper clippings about Siegel's death, correspondence related to his active participation in the University of Michigan President's Club and Beth Israel Congregation, and various files from committees Siegel served on.
  - Beth Israel Congregation, 1963-1966 (Box 2)
  - Clippings, 1970-1975 (Box 2)
  - Estate Files, 1978 (Box 2)
  - General, 1970 (Box 2)
  - Research Policy Committee, 1964-1965 (Box 2)
  - University of Michigan President's Club, 1962-1967 (Box 2)
  - United Jewish Appeal Emergency Fund, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Lecture on Electromagnetic Diagnostics of the Moon, July 10, 1961, 1 reel-to-reel tape; 7 in., 3 3/4 ips (Box 2)